Mss.Rec.80 Mss.Rec.80
American Philosophical Society
Quileute recordings
1969-1970
Mss.Rec.80
American Philosophical Society
14.0 Reel(s)
Linguistic field recordings of the Quileute language based on Manuel J. Andrade's "Quileute Texts" (Columbia University Press, 1931), made by Eric Hamp. The recordings consist of Hamp reading back from Andrade's transcription of Quileute texts to Beatrice Black, a Quileute-speaking consultant, who repeats them in the correct pronunciation, provides explanation, and suggests corrections. Includes occasional discussions in English, with some infrequent English translations of the text. Texts included are primarily Quileute legends and folklore. Also included are conversations and discussions about basket making, local history, family history, education, potlatches, and Quileute vocabulary relating to calculating age, digging clams, gender-specific forms of address, names of rivers, and other miscellaneous terms. Recorded at Taholah, Washington, in August 1969 and November 1970.
14 sound tape reels (29 hr., 59 min.): analog, 3 3/4 ips, 2 track, mono; 7 in.
Andrade, Manuel José, 1885-1941
Black, Beatrice
Hamp, Eric P.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Eric Hamp. This material was recorded with the assistance of a Phillips Fund grant.
Basket making; Indians of North America--Washington (State)--Olympic Peninsula; La Push (Wash.); Monsters--Folklore; Potlatch; Quileute Indians--Folklore; Quileute Indians--History; Quileute Indians--Social life and customs; Quileute language--Texts; Raven (Legendary character)--Legends; Sound recordings
- Audio recordings
  - Text 18: Q'wäeti' deceives Dásk'iya' [incomplete], 1969-08; 01-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:07:27; Black, Beatrice; Hamp, Eric P.
    Scope and Contents note
    This program consists of the researcher reading back a text in Quileute from Manuel J. Andrade's "Quileute Texts" (see Related Resource) to a Quileute-speaking consultant who assists in pronunciation, provides explanation, and suggests corrections. Interactions in English, with infrequent English translations of the text. Identical to "Text 18: Q'wäeti' deceives Dásk'iya' [2 of 2]" (APSdigrec_1986) from collection APSREC073 by the same collector. See Related Recording.
    Existence and Location of Originals note
    This file is a compressed, digitized version of the original. The APS Library maintains the original format (Sound tape reel) as well as an uncompressed digitized version of this recording.
    Monsters--Folklore; Quileute Indians--Folklore; Quileute language--Texts; Taholah (Wash.)
  - Text 19: Dásk'iya' is killed by a girl, 1969-08; 01-02; 1.0 .mp3; 00:22:43; Black, Beatrice; Hamp, Eric P.
    This program consists of the researcher reading back a text in Quileute from Manuel J. Andrade's "Quileute Texts" (see Related Resource) to a Quileute-speaking consultant who assists in pronunciation, provides explanation, and suggests corrections. Interactions in English, with infrequent English translations of the text. Identical to "Text 19: Dásk'iya' is killed by a girl" (APSdigrec_1987) from collection APSREC073 by the same collector. See Related Recording.
  - Text 20: Devil-fish kills Dásk'iya', 1969-08; 01-03; 1.0 .mp3; 00:18:06; Black, Beatrice; Hamp, Eric P.
    This program consists of the researcher reading back a text in Quileute from Manuel J. Andrade's "Quileute Texts" (see Related Resource) to a Quileute-speaking consultant who assists in pronunciation, provides explanation, and suggests corrections. Interactions in English, with infrequent English translations of the text. Identical to "Text 20: Devil-fish kills Dásk'iya'" (APSdigrec_1988) from collection APSREC073 by the same collector. See Related Recording.
    Quileute Indians--Folklore; Quileute language--Texts; Taholah (Wash.)
  - Conversation in English and Quileute, 1969-08-19; 01-04; 1.0 .mp3; 00:00:35; Black, Beatrice; Hamp, Eric P.
    Quileute language; Taholah (Wash.)
  - Text 21: The man who was left on a rock [incomplete], 1969-08-20; 01-05; 1.0 .mp3; 00:35:41; Black, Beatrice; Hamp, Eric P.
    This program consists of the researcher reading back a text in Quileute from Manuel J. Andrade's "Quileute Texts" (see Related Resource) to a Quileute-speaking consultant who assists in pronunciation, provides explanation, and suggests corrections. Interactions in English, with infrequent English translations of the text. The beginning of the story is not found on the original recording. This program begins approximately 33 lines after the story's beginning in the source text. The length of the entire story in the source text is 52 lines.
  - Text 22: The girl who was left on a tree [1 of 2], 1969-08-20; 01-06; 1.0 .mp3; 00:53:13; Black, Beatrice; Hamp, Eric P.
    This program consists of the researcher reading back a text in Quileute from Manuel J. Andrade's "Quileute Texts" (see Related Resource) to a Quileute-speaking consultant who assists in pronunciation, provides explanation, and suggests corrections. Interactions in English, with infrequent English translations of the text.
  - Text 22: The girl who was left on a tree [2 of 2], 1969-08-20; 02-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:09:40; Black, Beatrice; Hamp, Eric P.
    This program consists of the researcher reading back a text in Quileute from Manuel J. Andrade's "Quileute Texts" (see Related Resource) to a Quileute-speaking consultant who assists in pronunciation, provides explanation, and suggests corrections. Interactions in English, with infrequent English translations of the text. The majority of this program consists of a discussion of a rude word used by someone in the story.
    Quileute Indians--Folklore; Quileute language--Obscene words; Quileute language--Texts; Taholah (Wash.)
  - Text 23: The two brothers [1 of 3], 1969-08-20; 02-02; 1.0 .mp3; 00:59:10; Black, Beatrice; Hamp, Eric P.
    Brothers--Folklore; Quileute Indians--Folklore; Quileute language--Texts; Taholah (Wash.)
  - Text 23: The two brothers [2 of 3], 1969-08-20; 02-03; 1.0 .mp3; 00:04:51; Black, Beatrice; Hamp, Eric P.
  - Text 23: The two brothers [3 of 3], 1969-08-23; 02-04; 1.0 .mp3; 00:23:57; Black, Beatrice; Hamp, Eric P.
  - Text 24: Wadswad's exploit [1 of 2], 1969-08-23; 02-05; 1.0 .mp3; 00:17:24; Black, Beatrice; Hamp, Eric P.
  - Text 24: Wadswad's exploit [2 of 2], 1969-08-23; 02-06; 1.0 .mp3; 00:15:06; Black, Beatrice; Hamp, Eric P.
  - Text 25: Rabbit and Wolf, 1969-08-23; 03-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:07:01; Black, Beatrice; Hamp, Eric P.
    Quileute Indians--Folklore; Quileute language--Texts; Rabbits--Folklore; Taholah (Wash.); Wolves--Folklore
  - Quileute term for digging clams, 1969-08-23; 03-02; 1.0 .mp3; 00:00:32; Black, Beatrice; Hamp, Eric P.
    Clamming; Quileute language; Taholah (Wash.)
  - Text 26: The star husbands [1 of 5], 1969-08-24; 03-03; 1.0 .mp3; 00:12:02; Black, Beatrice; Hamp, Eric P.
    Quileute Indians--Folklore; Quileute language--Texts; Stars--Mythology; Taholah (Wash.)
  - Text 26: The star husbands [2 of 5], 1969-08-24; 03-04; 1.0 .mp3; 00:57:08; Black, Beatrice; Hamp, Eric P.
  - Text 26: The star husbands [3 of 5], 1969-08-24; 03-05; 1.0 .mp3; 00:49:19; Black, Beatrice; Hamp, Eric P.
  - Text 26: The star husbands [4 of 5], 1969-08-24; 03-06; 1.0 .mp3; 00:18:21; Black, Beatrice; Hamp, Eric P.
  - Text 26: The star husbands [5 of 5], 1969-08-24; 04-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:21:18; Black, Beatrice; Hamp, Eric P.
  - Quileute names for rivers, 1969-08-24; 04-02; 1.0 .mp3; 00:04:24; Black, Beatrice; Hamp, Eric P.
    Names, Geographical--Washington (State)--Olympic Peninsula; Quileute language; Rivers--Washington (State)--Olympic Peninsula; Taholah (Wash.)
  - Text 28: The theft of light [1 of 2], 1969-08-24; 04-03; 1.0 .mp3; 00:05:10; Black, Beatrice; Hamp, Eric P.
    Light--Mythology; Quileute Indians--Folklore; Quileute language--Texts; Taholah (Wash.)
  - Text 28: The theft of light [2 of 2], 1969-08-24; 04-04; 1.0 .mp3; 00:50:23; Black, Beatrice; Hamp, Eric P.
  - Text 31: Q'wäeti' plays a trick on Shark [1 of 3], 1969-08-24; 04-05; 1.0 .mp3; 00:16:18; Black, Beatrice; Hamp, Eric P.
    Quileute Indians--Folklore; Quileute language--Texts; Sharks--Folklore; Taholah (Wash.)
  - Conversation on education and potlatches, 1969-08-24; 04-06; 1.0 .mp3; 00:07:24; Black, Beatrice; Hamp, Eric P.
    La Push (Wash.); Potlatch; Quileute Indians--Education; Quileute language; Taholah (Wash.)
  - Text 31: Q'wäeti' plays a trick on Shark [2 of 3], 1969-08-24; 04-07; 1.0 .mp3; 00:26:55; Black, Beatrice; Hamp, Eric P.
  - Text 31: Q'wäeti' plays a trick on Shark [3 of 3], 1969-08-25; 05-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:13:44; Black, Beatrice; Hamp, Eric P.
  - Text 32: Q'wäeti' and the wolves, 1969-08-25; 05-02; 1.0 .mp3; 00:47:21; Black, Beatrice; Hamp, Eric P.
    Quileute Indians--Folklore; Quileute language--Texts; Taholah (Wash.); Wolves--Folklore
  - Text 33: The origin of death [1 of 2], 1969-08-25; 05-03; 1.0 .mp3; 00:04:44; Black, Beatrice; Hamp, Eric P.
    Death--Folklore; Quileute Indians--Folklore; Quileute language--Texts; Raven (Legendary character)--Legends; Taholah (Wash.)
  - Text 33: The origin of death [2 of 2], 1969-08-25; 05-04; 1.0 .mp3; 00:22:11; Black, Beatrice; Hamp, Eric P.
  - Text 34: Raven loses his son [1 of 3], 1969-08-26; 05-05; 1.0 .mp3; 00:10:42; Black, Beatrice; Hamp, Eric P.
    Quileute Indians--Folklore; Quileute language--Texts; Raven (Legendary character)--Legends; Taholah (Wash.)
  - Text 34: Raven loses his son [2 of 3], 1969-08-26; 05-06; 1.0 .mp3; 00:32:59; Black, Beatrice; Hamp, Eric P.
  - Text 34: Raven loses his son [3 of 3], 1969-08-26; 06-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:05:09; Black, Beatrice; Hamp, Eric P.
  - Text 35: The origin of death, 1969-08-26; 06-02; 1.0 .mp3; 00:04:51; Black, Beatrice; Hamp, Eric P.
  - Text 36: Raven orders Deer to weep, 1969-08-27; 06-03; 1.0 .mp3; 00:42:15; Black, Beatrice; Hamp, Eric P.
    Deer--Folklore; Quileute Indians--Folklore; Quileute language--Texts; Raven (Legendary character)--Legends; Taholah (Wash.)
  - Text 37: Raven and Fish-Duck, 1969-08-27; 06-04; 1.0 .mp3; 00:13:16; Black, Beatrice; Hamp, Eric P.
    Ducks--Folklore; Quileute Indians--Folklore; Quileute language--Texts; Raven (Legendary character)--Legends; Taholah (Wash.)
  - Text 38: Raven and King-fisher, 1969-08-27; 06-05; 1.0 .mp3; 00:16:18; Black, Beatrice; Hamp, Eric P.
    Kingfishers--Folklore; Quileute Indians--Folklore; Quileute language--Texts; Raven (Legendary character)--Legends; Taholah (Wash.)
  - Text 39: Raven and Bear, 1969-08-27; 06-06; 1.0 .mp3; 00:21:31; Black, Beatrice; Hamp, Eric P.
    Bears--Folklore; Quileute Indians--Folklore; Quileute language--Texts; Raven (Legendary character)--Legends; Taholah (Wash.)
  - Text 40: Raven loses his daughter, 1969-08-27; 06-07; 1.0 .mp3; 00:06:39; Black, Beatrice; Hamp, Eric P.
  - Text 41: Raven gambles, 1969-08-27; 06-08; 1.0 .mp3; 00:12:51; Black, Beatrice; Hamp, Eric P.
    This program consists of the researcher reading back a text in Quileute from Manuel J. Andrade's "Quileute Texts" (see Related Resource) to a Quileute-speaking consultant who assists in pronunciation, provides explanation, and suggests corrections. Interactions in English, with infrequent English translations of the text. From 7:51 to 8:17 there is a passage identified in the source text as being in the Quinault language.
  - Conversation on miscellaneous Quileute words and gender-specific forms of address, 1969-08-27; 06-09; 1.0 .mp3; 00:09:28; Black, Beatrice; Hamp, Eric P.
    Quileute language; Quileute language--Grammar; Taholah (Wash.)
  - Text 42: Dásk'iya' is killed by a girl, 1969-08-28; 07-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:14:55; Black, Beatrice; Hamp, Eric P.
  - Text 43: Dásk'iya' is killed by a young man, 1969-08-28; 07-02; 1.0 .mp3; 00:18:18; Black, Beatrice; Hamp, Eric P.
  - Text 44: Dásk'iya' is killed by Devil-fish, 1969-08-28; 07-03; 1.0 .mp3; 00:14:43; Black, Beatrice; Hamp, Eric P.
  - Text 45: Dásk'iya' is killed by Q'wäeti' [1 of 2], 1969-08-28; 07-04; 1.0 .mp3; 00:17:50; Black, Beatrice; Hamp, Eric P.
  - Text 45: Dásk'iya' is killed by Q'wäeti' [2 of 2], 1969-08-28; 07-05; 1.0 .mp3; 00:03:24; Black, Beatrice; Hamp, Eric P.
  - Text 46: The elks kill the wolves, 1969-08-28; 07-06; 1.0 .mp3; 00:36:54; Black, Beatrice; Hamp, Eric P.
    Elk--Folklore; Quileute Indians--Folklore; Quileute language--Texts; Taholah (Wash.); Wolves--Folklore
  - Text 47: Wren and Bear [1 of 2], 1969-08-28; 07-07; 1.0 .mp3; 00:25:36; Black, Beatrice; Hamp, Eric P.
    Bears--Folklore; Quileute Indians--Folklore; Quileute language--Texts; Taholah (Wash.); Wrens--Folklore
  - Text 47: Wren and Bear [2 of 2], 1969-08-28; 08-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:07:49; Black, Beatrice; Hamp, Eric P.
  - Quileute words and phrases taken from Manuel J. Andrade's "Quileute", 1969-08-29; 08-02; 1.0 .mp3; 00:43:43; Black, Beatrice; Hamp, Eric P.
    Quileute language--Glossaries, vocabularies, etc.; Taholah (Wash.)
  - Text 48: Rabbit and East Wind, 1969-08-29; 08-03; 1.0 .mp3; 00:12:35; Black, Beatrice; Hamp, Eric P.
    Quileute Indians--Folklore; Quileute language--Texts; Rabbits--Folklore; Taholah (Wash.); Winds--Folklore
  - Text 49: The Woman who married a dog [1 of 2], 1969-08-29; 08-04; 1.0 .mp3; 01:04:00; Black, Beatrice; Hamp, Eric P.
    Dogs--Folklore; Quileute Indians--Folklore; Quileute Indians--Social life and customs; Quileute language--Texts; Taholah (Wash.); Whaling
  - Text 49: The Woman who married a dog [2 of 2], 1969-08-29; 09-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:55:06; Black, Beatrice; Hamp, Eric P.
  - Text 50: The dog children [1 of 2], 1969-08-31; 09-02; 1.0 .mp3; 00:09:49; Black, Beatrice; Hamp, Eric P.
    Dogs--Folklore; Quileute Indians--Folklore; Quileute language--Texts; Taholah (Wash.)
  - Text 50: The dog children [2 of 2], 1969-08-31; 09-03; 1.0 .mp3; 01:03:20; Black, Beatrice; Hamp, Eric P.
  - Text 51: The woman who married Shark [1 of 2], 1969-08-31; 10-01; 1.0 .mp3; 01:05:04; Black, Beatrice; Hamp, Eric P.
  - Text 51: The woman who married Shark [2 of 2], 1969-08-31; 10-02; 1.0 .mp3; 00:06:38; Black, Beatrice; Hamp, Eric P.
  - Text 52: The man who married Thunder-Bird's daughter [1 of 2], 1969-08-31; 10-03; 1.0 .mp3; 00:58:25; Black, Beatrice; Hamp, Eric P.
    Quileute Indians--Folklore; Quileute language--Texts; Taholah (Wash.); Thunderbird (Legendary character)--Legends
  - Text 52: The man who married Thunder-Bird's daughter [2 of 2], 1969-09-01; 11-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:22:37; Black, Beatrice; Hamp, Eric P.
  - Text 53: The Two Fishermen [1 of 2], 1969-09-02; 11-02; 1.0 .mp3; 00:32:37; Black, Beatrice; Hamp, Eric P.
    Quileute Indians--Fishing; Quileute Indians--Folklore; Quileute language--Texts; Taholah (Wash.)
  - Text 53: The Two Fishermen [2 of 2], 1969-09-02; 11-03; 1.0 .mp3; 00:25:41; Black, Beatrice; Hamp, Eric P.
    This program consists of the researcher reading back a text in Quileute from Manuel J. Andrade's "Quileute Texts" (see Related Resource) to a Quileute-speaking consultant who assists in pronunciation, provides explanation, and suggests corrections. Interactions in English, with infrequent English translations of the text. At 3:32 there are 3 seconds of silence representing a gap on the original recording. In the gap, lines 28-32 from the original source text are missing.
  - Text 54: The Man who Became a Hair-Seal [1 of 3], 1970-11-21; 11-04; 1.0 .mp3; 00:42:45; Black, Beatrice; Hamp, Eric P.
    This program consists of the researcher reading back a text in Quileute from Manuel J. Andrade's "Quileute Texts" (see Related Resource) to a Quileute-speaking consultant who assists in pronunciation, provides explanation, and suggests corrections. Interactions in English, with infrequent English translations of the text. At 25:07 there are 3 seconds of silence representing a gap in the original recording. Due to this gap, most of lines 23-24 from the original source text are missing.
    Quileute Indians--Folklore; Quileute language--Texts; Sealing; Taholah (Wash.)
  - Text 54: The Man who Became a Hair-Seal [2 of 3], 1970-11-21; 12-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:54:21; Black, Beatrice; Hamp, Eric P.
  - Text 54: The Man who Became a Hair-Seal [3 of 3], 1970-11-21; 12-02; 1.0 .mp3; 00:48:21; Black, Beatrice; Hamp, Eric P.
  - Text 55: Three Hunters are Taken to Seal's Home [1 of 2], 1970-11-21; 12-03; 1.0 .mp3; 00:28:59; Black, Beatrice; Hamp, Eric P.
  - Text 55: Three Hunters are Taken to Seal's Home [2 of 2], 1970-11-21; 13-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:36:02; Black, Beatrice; Hamp, Eric P.
  - Conversation on seasons and calculating people's ages, 1970-11-21; 13-02; 1.0 .mp3; 00:10:24; Black, Beatrice; Hamp, Eric P.
    Age; Birds--Washington (State)--Olympic Peninsula; Quileute Indians--Social life and customs; Quileute language; Seasons; Taholah (Wash.)
  - Text 56: The Origin of the Man in the Moon [1 of 5], 1970-11-22; 13-03; 1.0 .mp3; 00:17:13; Black, Beatrice; Hamp, Eric P.
    Moon--Folklore; Quileute Indians--Folklore; Quileute language--Texts; Taholah (Wash.)
  - Text 56: The Origin of the Man in the Moon [2 of 5], 1970-11-22; 13-04; 1.0 .mp3; 00:06:08; Black, Beatrice; Hamp, Eric P.
  - Conversation on family history and local history, 1970-11-22; 13-05; 1.0 .mp3; 00:31:33; Black, Beatrice; Hamp, Eric P.
    Indians of North America--Washington (State)--Olympic Peninsula; Quileute Indians--History; Quileute Indians--Social life and customs; Reagan, Albert B., 1871-1936; Taholah (Wash.)
  - Text 56: The Origin of the Man in the Moon [3 of 5], 1970-11-22; 13-06; 1.0 .mp3; 00:17:13; Black, Beatrice; Hamp, Eric P.
  - Text 56: The Origin of the Man in the Moon [4 of 5], 1970-11-22; 13-07; 1.0 .mp3; 00:11:18; Black, Beatrice; Hamp, Eric P.
  - Text 56: The Origin of the Man in the Moon [5 of 5], 1970-11-22; 14-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:38:24; Black, Beatrice; Hamp, Eric P.
  - Text 57: The Origin of Potlatch [1 of 2], 1970-11-22; 14-02; 1.0 .mp3; 00:28:24; Black, Beatrice; Hamp, Eric P.
    Birds--Folklore; Potlatch; Quileute Indians--Folklore; Quileute language--Texts; Taholah (Wash.)
  - Text 57: The Origin of Potlatch [2 of 2], 1970-11-22; 14-03; 1.0 .mp3; 00:14:29; Black, Beatrice; Hamp, Eric P.
  - Conversation about baskets, 1970-11-22; 14-04; 1.0 .mp3; 00:03:13; Black, Beatrice; Hamp, Eric P.
    Basket making; Quileute Indians--Fishing; Quileute Indians--Social life and customs; Taholah (Wash.)